In this video we will revisit the license check program from last time.
在本视频中，我们将重新浏览，上次的许可证检查程序。
You can get the same compiled 64bit binary from github and you can also watch the last
从Github，您可以得到相同的编译 64位二进制文件，你也可以观看
video where I went into more detail how to crack this simple program.
上个视频，详细介绍了关于如何破解这个简单的程序。
I will show now different simple tools and techniques that exist to analyse a program
现在我，将展示分析程序，现有不同的简单工具和技术
like that to circumvent the license check.
以此，规避许可证检查。
This should show you that there are a variety of different ways how to solve this challenge.
这应该能，向你证明其实有很多种方式，可以完成这一挑战。
The file command is very useful to check what kind of files you have.
file 命令，对检查你拥有的文件种类，很有用。
So ‘file’ on our binary says it’s a ELF 64-bit executable for Linux.
所以，"file"二进制文件，说它是用于 Linux 的 ELF 64位可执行文件。
You can also do ‘file *’ to get the information on all files in the directory.
您还可以执行"file *"，以获取目录中的所有文件信息。
And it then also finds the C source code here.
然后它也会，在这里找到 C源代码。
So that’s very useful.
所以，这很有用。
Let’s open the program in a text editor like vim.
让我们在文本编辑器(像vim)中，打开程序。
As you can see it looks very weird.
如你所见，这看起来很奇怪。
I have introduced ASCII before, so you know that every character has assigned a number.
我以前介绍过ASCII，所以你知道每个字符，都分配了一个数字。
But there are numbers that don’t have a printable character assigned.
但这里有些数字没有，已分配的可打印字符。
If you look at the man page of ascii, you see that for example value 0 to hex 1f are
如果你看一下ascii的手册(man)页，你会发现例如，(hex)1f 的 值 0   不是普通字符。
And ascii is also only defined up to hex 7F or 127.
而ASCII(规则编码)最高，只定义到了，(hex)7f 或者说 127。
But because our computer works with bytes, so 8 bit, this number can range from 0 to
但是因为我们的计算机可以处理字节，所以8位(字节)，这个(数值)范围可以
255, And ascii only uses half of them.
从 0 到 255 ，而ASCII只使用其中的一半。
So all those weird blue values in vim are such numbers that don’t have a printable
所以Vim中所有奇怪的蓝色值，都是没有对应分配字符的数字
You can also do a hexdump of the file, to get the actual values.
您还可以对该文件执行 hexdump，以获取实际值。
‘hexdump -C license_1’ and you can see that there are many many 0s in the file.
"hexdump -C license_1"，您可以看到文件中，有许多 0。
hexdump displays them as dots, but in vim they are the blue stuff.
hexdump 将它们显示为 点，但在 vim 中它们是蓝色的东西。
But when you look closely there are quite a few meaningful strings in there.
但是，当你仔细看一些有意义的字符串的时候。
For example right at the beginning “ELF”, which is a magic value, hinting that this
例如，就是"ELF"开头，这是一个神奇的值，暗示着文件，是可执行文件。
You also can find some strings to libraries such as libc, which defines functions such
您还可以找到一些库的字符串，例如 libc，它定义了，如 printf 和 strcmp 函数
And here we also see strings we know, the “Checking License”, “Access Granted”,
在这里，我们也看到了我们知道的字符串，"正在检查许可证"，"已授予访问权限"，
“WRONG!” and “Usage” message.
"错了！"和"用法"消息。
And also this weird looking “AAAA-ZION-42-OK” string.
还有，这个奇怪的"aaaa-zion-42-ok"字符串。
hmmhmh…
嗯，噢，哦…
Remember from last video that there was a string compare in it?
从上一个视频中，记得字符串比较吗？
Might get the license key we enter compared to this string?
可能，我们输入的许可证密钥，就是与这个字符串做比较的吗？
Let’s try it!
让我们试试看！
Access Granted.
准许访问。
Indeed!
的确啊！
The license key of this program was in there all along.
这个程序的密钥，一直在呀。
There is a great tool called ‘strings’ that is doing what we just did, just nicer.
有一个很棒的工具叫做"strings"，能做我们刚刚做的事情，但更好。
It will scan a file and prints out all printable character sequences with at least a certain
它将扫描一个文件，并打印出所有可打印的，至少有一个特定长度的字符序列
So let’s try it with ‘strings license_1’.
所以，让我们用"strings license_1"来试试。
And there are our strings.
没错，这就是我们的字符串。
Last time we used gdb to read the disassembly and also debug the program.
上次，我们用gdb读取，反汇编，和调试了程序。
This time let’s just use objdump for the disassembly.
这次我们就用 objdump 反汇编。
‘objdump -d license_1’.
"objdump -d license_1"
You notice that this file has a lot of more code than just the ‘main’ function.
你注意到这个文件，还有很多代码，不仅仅是"main"函数。
That is because the compiler puts a bit more stuff into the actual binary.
这是因为，编译器把一些东西，放入实际的二进制文件中。
You know, computers are a little bit more complex than they seem at first.
你知道，计算机，在一开始看起来复杂。
But all of this is just standard stuff you basically find in any gcc compiled binary.
但这基本上，都是实际的 gcc 二进制文件会有的标准信息。
And usually only the user created functions like main are interesting to us.
而通常，只有用户创建的函数，像 main ，我们才会有兴趣。
Objdump can be used to get a looot of more information about this program.
objdump 可用于获取更多有关此程序的信息。
Let’s print everything with ‘objdump -c license_1’ and pipe it into less for easier
让我们用"objdump -c license_1"打印它的所有，并将其导入 less 命令管道中，以便于导航查看。
So first it says the file is a elf binary for the x86-64 architecture.
所以首先，它说这个文件是一个 ELF二进制文件，属于 x86-64体系结构。
The stack is not executable, indicated by the missing ‘x’, which is interesting
栈不可执行，指示说缺少了"x"，噢有趣。
once we will look at classic buffer overflows.
一旦，我们看到经典的缓冲区溢出。
And maybe the last interesting info are the sections.
也许最后一个感兴趣的信息是 sections。
We can see here where certain data will later end up in memory.
我们可以在这里，看到某些数据之后，在内存中结束。
Interesting for us are the .text section.
感兴趣的是 .text 部分。
This section holds our code and it starts at address 4004d0 and is hex 1e2 big.
这个部分，保存了我们的代码，它从 地址4004D0 开始，是 (hex)1E2 大小。
And if you check the address where the main function was, you will notice that it’s
如果，你查一下 main 函数的地址，你会注意到，就在这里。
The other interesting section is .rodata, which is the read only data section.
另一个感兴趣的部分是 .rodata，这是只读数据部分。
So our strings can be found in there.
所以我们的字符串，可以在这找到。
If you open up gdb and break at the strcmp, you can check the registers.
如果你打开 gdb，并在strcmp处断点，你可以查一下寄存器。
And one of the registers will have an address in from this .rodata section.
其中一个寄存器，将有个，这 .rodata部分的地址。
You can print this address with x/s, and voila, there is our key again.
你可以用 x/s 打印这个地址，瞧，又有密钥啦。
Let’s have a look at another active tool.
让我们看看另一个可行的工具。
It’s called strace and it can trace system calls and signals.
它叫strace，可以追踪系统调用和信号。
When I introduced programming in C, we used printf to print text.
当我介绍C语言的编程时，我们使用 printf 打印文本。
That was a nice function that we added to our program from the libc library.
帮我们的程序增加了一个很好的函数，它来自 libc 库。
But printf is just a wrapper around a function that the linux system itself provides us.
但是 printf 只是一个函数的包装器，而这是 Linux系统本身为我们提供的。
Linux itself offers many different kind of functions called syscalls.
Linux本身提供了许多不同类型的函数，都调用了syscalls。
You can read more about them in the man page to syscalls.
你可以在手册(man)页上，看到更多关于它们（syscalls）的信息。
One of those functions is ‘write’.
其中一个函数是"write"。
And write can be used to write text to the standard output, which we can read on the
可用于，将文本写入标准输出，这样我们就可以在控制台读到。
So let’s execute the license program with strace.
那么让我们用strace，执行我们的检查程序
The first line is execve, which is the function that tells the linux kernel to now execute
第一行是 execve，这是函数，它告诉Linux内核，现在执行程序 license_1
And then a lot of magic happens that we ignore from now.
不过现在，我们先忽略下开头的魔法。
And somewhere all the way at the bottom here, the code that I have written starts.
在底部的某个地方，我写的代码开始了。
And you can here see the write syscalls that were executed with the text that we know.
你可以在这里，看到 write syscalls 是用我们知道的文本执行的。
Interesting, huh?
有趣，吧？
There is another cool tool called ltrace.
还有一个很酷的工具，叫 ltrace。
Similar to strace it traces certain functions.
与strace类似，它跟踪某些函数。
But this time it traces library functions.
但这次它，跟踪库函数。
Functions like printf or strcmp come from the libc library.
printf 或strcmp等函数，都来自库。
So ltrace can show us their occurrence.
所以ltrace，可以告诉我们它们的发生状况。
So first you can see the printf.
所以首先，你可以看到 printf。
And then comes the strcmp.
然后是 strcmp。
And it shows us the actual strings it compares.
它向我们展示了，比较的实际字符串。
So that also tells us how the license check works in a cool way.
它还用一种酷的方式，告诉我们程序的工作。
Let’s thow this file into a graphical user interface.
让我们把这个文件，转换成一个图形用户接口。
I will use hopper on mac.
我将在Mac上使用 Hopper。
As you may know IDAPro is very expensive.
你可能知道，IDAPro很贵。
But hopper is a great alternative which is actually affordable.
但是 Hopper是一个很好的选择，可以负担得起。
Hopper sees that it is a ELF executable and it can automatically analyse it for us.
Hopper会发现这文件是一个ELF可执行文件，并且自动为我们分析。
It places our curser at a function called start.
它将我们的光标，放在一个函数调用的开头，不是 main。
Like we have seen with objdump before, there are a few more functions created by the compiler
就像我们之前看到的 objdump 那样，编译器还创建了几个函数吗？
and this here is the real entry point of the program.
这里才是程序的真实入口。
But what those functions are doing is not important right now.
但这些函数做的是什么，现在并不是很重要。
We are only interested in the main functionality.
我们只对 main 函数感兴趣。
So we can look for the main function in the list of labels.
所以我们可以在标签列表，查看 main 函数。
So here is our main function, like in gdb.
这是我们的 main 函数，就像在 gdb 中一样。
Just a bit more colorful and hopper can also show us with those arrows where branches are
只是稍微多些颜色，hopper也可以让我们看看这些箭头，所指向的分支
At the end of the last video I have already showed the control flow graph which you can
在上一视频的结尾，可以在右上角，显示了控制流程图
And a very cool feauter from hopper is the decompiler.
Hopper的一个非常酷的功能，是反编译程序。
Decompiling sounds like it would reverse assembler code back to C code.
反编译听起来，像将汇编代码，'反'回到C代码的形态。
But that is not easy.
但这没那么简单。
The compiler changes and optimises stuff and you just cannot simply reverse it.
因编译器更改并优化了内容，以至于你不能简单地'反'转它。
But hopper can guess how it might have looked like.
但是，Hopper能猜出它是什么样子的。
Sometimes it makes mistakes, but often it looks pretty good.
有时会出错，但通常情况下，看起来还不错。
So it shows us here how it checks if we have supplied a license key, and then it does the
它向我们展示了，检查是否提供了许可证密钥，然后
strcmp and prints either ‘Access Granted’ or ‘WRONG!’.
执行 strcmp 并打印 "已授予访问权限"或者是"错的！".
So that’s pretty cool.
所以，这真的很酷。
To the left you can also find a button to display all strings.
在左边你也可以找到一个按钮，会显示所有字符串。
And as you can see it also found the key.
正如你所看到的，它也找到了密钥啦
When you click on it it will jump to the address where the key is located.
当你点击它时，它会跳到密钥的地址位置。
And XREF stands for cross reference, that means this address is referenced somewhere.
xref代表交叉引用，意味着这个地址，在某个地方被引用。
We can follow that xref, and we can see that this is the assembler code where the address
我们可以顺着 xref，往下看，看到这是汇编代码
of the key is moved into the esi register.
（说）密钥地址移动到 esi 寄存器中。
This prepares the function parameters for the strcmp.
这为strcmp，准备函数参数
Some kids may have the opinion that mac users suck.
有些孩子，可能认为 Mac用户 'SUck'。
To please them we will install now radare2 by cloning the radare2 repository with git.
为了取悦他们，我们现在将安装radare2 ，具体是使用 Git 克隆它存储库。
You might have to install git with sudo apt-get install git.
你可能需要"sudo apt-get install git"，安装下git。
To install radare run sys/install.sh and wait.
要安装 radare2，请运行"sys/install.sh"并等待。
Once it’s installed you can go to the license_1 program and open it in radare with ‘r2 license_1’.
安装后，您可以去到 license_1 程序那里，用"r2 license_1"打开
You may remember this address from objdump earlier, this is the start of the text segment
你可能记得前面的 objdump 例子中的这个地址，这是我们代码的文本段开头
first run ‘aaa’, to automatically analyse an autoname functions.
首先运行"aaa"，自动化分析自动名称函数。
Then use ‘afl’ to print all functions that radare found.
然后使用"afl"，打印找到的所有函数。
Each character in radare means something.
radare2 中的每个字符，都有意义。
And with ? you always get information about what characters you can use.
通过 "?"符号 ，你总是能得到，您可以使用哪些字符的信息。
So ‘a’ performs analysis of code.
所以，"a"执行，代码分析。
‘a?’ shows us that we can append ‘f’ to analyse functions.
"a?"显示：我们可以附加'f'，来分析函数。
And ‘afl’ lists those functions.
"afl"列出了这些函数。
Makes sense, right?
有道理，对吧？
ok so afl shows us that it found a main function.
好的，'afl' 告诉我们，它找到了一个 main 函数。
Let’s change our current location with ‘s’ to seek to the location of the function main.
让我们用"s"更改当前位置，查找函数 main 的位置。
You can also use tab-completion here.
您也可以在这里，使用 tab补全。
Now the location in those brackets changed.
现在括号中的位置，改变了。
With ‘pdf’ we can print the disassembly of the current function.
使用"pdf"，我们可以打印，当前函数的反汇编代码。
Like hopper it shows us the disassembly with nice arrows where branches go to.
像 hopper 一样，它向我们展示了漂亮的箭头，表明分支的指向。
And it created comments for us with strings that are referenced in there.
它为我们创建了字符串注释，放在了被引用的位置。
You can also type capital VV to enter visual mode.
您还可以键入(大写) VV ，以进入Visual模式。
This shows you a control-graph view of this function.
这将向您显示，此函数控制-流程图的视图。
You can move it around with arrow keys.
你可以用箭头键，移动它。
The blue border indicates that we currently select this box.
蓝色边框表示，我们目前选择的框。
With Tab and Shift Tab you can select other blocks.
通过 Tab 和 shift 选项卡，您可以选择其他框。
When you have a block selected you can move the block with Shift + hjkl.
选定框后，可以用 Shift + hjkl 移动。
With ‘p’ you can cycle through different representations.
"p"，你可以圈住不同的表达式。
For example with our without the address in the beginning.
例如，不要开头的地址。
Or this minimalistic view, which is useful if you have a damn huge function.
或者这个极简的视图，如果你有一个巨大的函数，这会有用。
And with ? you can display a help.
然后，用'?'，您可以显示帮助。
This help tells you that capital R is the most important shortcut you will ever learn
这个帮助告诉你，(大写) R 是您能 radare2 中，学到的最重要的快捷命令。
So press Shift+R and be happy.
所以，按 Shift+R 键，和你高兴就好。
You can also use radare2 like gdb to debug this program.
也可以让 radare2，像 gdb 一样进行调试这个程序。
To do that start radare with -d flag.
为此，用-d标志，启动 radare2。
Seek to the main function, analyse all with ‘aaa’ and display the disassembly with
寻找 main 函数，分析所有"aaa"，并用"paf"显示反汇编
Now place a breakpoint at the start with ‘db’.
现在在开头"db"，放置一个断点。
Now go into Visual View with “VV” again.
现在再次使用"VV"，进入可视视图。
Like with vim you can enter command mode with ‘:’, where you type ‘:dc’ to run the
和Vim一样，您可以使用":"，在其中键入":dc"以运行程序。
Now we hit breakpoint 1.
现在，我们到达了断点1。
And if you look closely you notice rip in the first box.
如果你仔细看，你会发现第一个盒子的 rip 。
This shows us where the instruction pointer currently points to.
这向我们展示了，指令指针当前指向的位置。
With s you can step instructions.
使用 's'，您可以执行指令。
But we should use capital S, otherwise we follow functions which we don’t want to.
但是我们应该使用大写 S，否则我们追踪，我们不希望看到的函数。
So Shift+S to step further.
所以， shift+s 可以前一步。
Ah damn.
啊，该死的。
We didn’t supply a license key.
我们没有提供许可证密钥。
But you get the idea.
但，你明白了。
I hope this helps you to explore more tools and techniques.
我希望，这能帮助你，探索更多的工具和技术。
And remember that no tool is better than the other.
记住，没有什么工具是最强的。
They all have different features and representations of information.
它们都有不同的特性和信息表达。
It makes sense to master them all.
掌控它们是有意义的。
Except radare.
除 radare2 外。
Some say radare is the best.
有人说 radare2 是最好的。
But nobody ever masters radare.
但，从没有人能掌控 radare2。